Guide to the Loring McAlpin Collection on Gran Fury MSS.627
Fales Library and Special Collections
Loring McAlpin Collection on Gran Fury
1988-2019
Fales Library and Special Collections
McAlpin, Loring
MSS.627
2.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, 2 oversize folders in shared housing, and 1 flat file folder
2.00 Gigabytes in 34 computer files
Loring McAlpin is a documentary filmmaker and a founding member of the AIDS activist art collective Gran Fury. From 1988 to 1995, Gran Fury adapated strategies from artistic communities to interrupt traditional advertising spaces. The collective created posters, stickers, ephemera, and other graphic art alongisde ACT UP New York as part of larger organizing efforts to increase awareness during the AIDS crisis and to protest the silence, indifference, or hostility of many public figures during this time period. The Loring McAlpin Collection on Gran Fury (dated 1988-2019) consists of materials created and collected by McAlpin documenting the AIDS activist art collective Gran Fury. Materials in this collection include photographs, posters, design mock-ups, exhibition documentation, and interview transcripts. The materials document the group's efforts to educate and raise awareness of the AIDS crisis, as well as protest harmful AIDS policies. More broadly, the collection demonstrates the role of art within AIDS activism during the time period.
Scope and Contents
The Loring McAlpin Collection on Gran Fury (dated 1988-2019) consists of materials created and collected by McAlpin documenting the AIDS activist art collective Gran Fury. Materials in this collection include photographs, posters, design mock-ups, exhibition documentation, and interview transcripts. The materials document the group's efforts to educate and raise awareness of the AIDS crisis, as well as protest AIDS policies and indifference displayed by many public officials. The collection also documents more recent reflection on Gran Fury's work and impact in the broader AIDS activism sphere, as shown through gallery catalogs, ephemera, and interviews. In addition to its documentary focus on Gran Fury, this collection demonstrates the role of art within AIDS activism during the time period.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Loring McAlpin in March 2023; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.036.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Biographical Note
Loring McAlpin is a documentary filmmaker and a founding member of the AIDS activist art collective Gran Fury. From 1988 to 1995, Gran Fury created posters, stickers, ephemera, and other graphic art alongisde ACT UP New York as part of larger organizing efforts to increase awareness during the AIDS crisis and to protest the silence, indifference, or hostility of many public figures during this time period. McAlpin is also the founder of The Calamus Foundation, which works to support LGBTQ+ organizations that focus on social justice and civil rights pursuits.
Appraisal
Blank optical discs or discs with title cards only were appraised out of the collection.
AIDS activists.; AIDS (Disease); AIDS (Disease) and art -- United States.; Communication in art; Art -- Political aspects.; Social problems in art.; Art and society.; McAlpin, Loring; Gran Fury (Artists' collective); ACT UP New York (Organization)
- "1 in 61" / Wall Street Money, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Men: Condom Sticker, circa 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ohio Catalogue -- Death Statistics, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Medical Apartheid, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bloody Hand Poster, circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "The New York Crimes", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ArtForum Project, circa 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Art Against AIDS: "Kissing Doesn't Kill", 1988-1995
  - Digital File, circa 1988-1995; cuid39128
  - Paper (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Kitchen Calendar, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Politicians' Remarks, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Multiple Campaigns, circa 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11-12, Box 2, Folder 1, Box Shared Fales 097, Folder 2)
- Photographic Slides, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs, circa 1988-1995; cuid39129
- FBI Surveillance, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Good Luck" (New Museum), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Interviews and Panels, circa late 1990s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- ACT UP: An Activist's Timeline, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Original Art for 80WSE Gallery, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Gran Fury: Read My Lips" (NYU 80WSE Gallery), 2011 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Walker Art Center, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- RIOT Mural (LGBT Community Center), 2019 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "ACT UP New York: Activism, Art, and the AIDS Crisis, 1987-1993" (Harvard Art Museum), 2009 (Box Shared Fales 097, Folder 1)
- "AIDS Isn't Over for Anybody Until It's Over for Everybody" (The Decade Show: Frameworks for Identity in the 1980s), 1990 (Flat-file-folder 4 Right)